So I hope you enjoyed our first bash at Scrubbing Data, and that you are now looking through the code,
데이터 스크러빙 첫 번째 강습이 즐거우셨길 바랍니다 이제 코드를 훑어보며 데이터를 삭제했을
convincing yourself that I've done good things when I have cleansed the data and I haven't thrown out
때 좋은 일을 했다고 자신을 설득하세요 모델에 포함해야 할 건 아무것도 버리지
anything that we should be including for the model.
않았다고요
If you do find something like that, please let me know right away, because I love squeezing a bit
이런 걸 발견하시면 바로 알려주세요 모델에서 좀 더 비트 짜내고 결과를
more juice out of the model and making the results a little bit better, and changing the data.
좀 더 좋게 만들고 데이터를 바꾸는 걸 좋아하거든요
Improving the quality of the data that goes into the model has had by far the most profound impact on
모델로 들어가는 데이터의 품질 개선이 모델의 성능에 가장 큰
the performance of the model.
영향을 미쳤죠
You can spend huge amounts of time doing what they call hyperparameter tuning, which we will all be
hyperferameter 튜닝에 많은 시간을 할애할 수 있습니다. 한동안
doing for for a while to try and squeeze a little tiny bit of juice out of your model and make it a
이 방법으로 모델에서 쥐어짜낸 비트들을 통해 결과를 예측하는
little bit better at predicting outcomes as we try and go head to head against frontier models, which
게 더 쉬워질 겁니다. 물론 개척 모델과 맞붙어서 어려운 작업을
is going to be hard.
해야겠죠.
Um, but it turns out that improving the data quality of what goes in is the easiest and most effective
하지만 데이터 품질을 향상시키는 게 가장 쉽고 효과적인 방법이에요
So that's why it's worth spending the time doing it.
그래서 시간을 들여야 하는 거죠
And in that last Jupyter notebook, we we really worked on numbers one, two and three on this list,
그리고 마지막 주피터 노트에는 이 목록의 1번, 2번, 3번 4번, 5번까지
and some of four and five.
작업했어요
We've got more of four and five to go, but most important is that you look through that Isom class
아직 4개와 5개가 더 남았지만 가장 중요한 건 아이솜 클래스를
and see how it's doing its thing yourself.
직접 살펴보는 거예요
Now just before we we we wrap up, I do want to measure and mention again the topic of performance evaluation,
마무리하기 전에 다시 한번 측정과 평가 주제를 언급하고 싶습니다 이 모델로
how we're going to decide whether or not we have actually succeeded in our goals with this model.
목표 달성을 달성했는지 어떻게 결정하는지에 관해서요
Uh, there are, as I mentioned a while back, these two kinds of of metrics that you can use to evaluate
앞서 말씀드렸듯이 성능을 평가할 때 사용하는 두 가지 측정법이 있어요
There are model centric metrics which are more in the sort of data scientist's domain of understanding
모델 중심 지표라는 게 있는데 모델이 수학적으로 얼마나 잘 작동하는지
how how well your model is performing mathematically.
이해하는 데이터 과학자의 영역에 속하죠
Uh, and then there are outcome business centric metrics, which are the ones that will resonate with
그리고 결과 비즈니스 중심 지표가 있습니다 사용자, 스폰서,
the, the the user, the sponsor, the the CEO.
CEO의 마음을 사로잡는 지표죠
They're the ultimate goals of the project.
그게 이 프로젝트의 궁극적인 목표예요
The model centric ones are much more directly measurable by the model, and can usually be measured
모델 중심의 것은 모델이 훨씬 직접 측정합니다 훈련과 최적화 과정에서
while it's training and optimized.
측정할 수 있죠
The business centric ones are the ones that matter the most, but not necessarily as immediately tied
비즈니스 중심의 것이 가장 중요하지만 모델과 바로 연결될 필요는
to the model.
없죠
Although in our case, we have this wonderful luxury of having business centric metrics which are going
물론 우리 같은 경우에는 비즈니스 중심 지표가 있어서 호사를 누리고 있죠
to be tied to the model and are going to be great first on the model centric metrics.
모델 중심 지표에서 가장 성공적일 거예요
So you'll often hear talk of training loss and validation loss that training losses is is the loss with
훈련의 손실이나 검증의 손실이란 말을 종종 듣게 될 겁니다 훈련의 손실은 훈련 세트와 함께 잃는
the training set.
거죠
Validation loss is with the validation set, which is a part of the data that you've held back.
검증 손실은 검증 집합과 함께 발생합니다 검증 집합은 데이터의 일부죠
And this is going to be a metric that the model will calculate that we'll talk more about later, and
모델은 이 측정법을 통해 계산할 겁니다 나중에 자세히
we'll see it happening.
살펴보죠
And during the course of training you will see your training loss hopefully gradually going down and
훈련 과정에서 손실된 훈련량이 점차 줄어들 겁니다
down and down, which means that the model is getting more and more accurate at doing its task.
모델이 작업을 점점 더 정확하게 수행한다는 뜻이죠
Um uh, and there are some more sophisticated data science metrics that uh, we will also be looking
좀 더 정교한 데이터 과학 지표도 있는데 다양한 관점을 살펴볼
at at various points.
거예요
There's one called the root mean squared log error.
루트 평제곱 로그 에러라는 게 있어요
RMSE l.
RMSE l요
And the benefit of this particular error is that it's something that will both penalize the model if
이런 오류의 장점은 모델이 절대적으로 잘못되거나 퍼센트를 기준으로
it's if it's wrong on an, on an absolute basis and on a, on a percentage basis in different ways.
하면 여러 면에서 감점을 받는다는 거죠
And it's not going to unfairly penalize the model if it's out by a few dollars on a low priced item.
저가 제품에 몇 달러 차이로 불이익을 당해도 모델에게 부당하지 않아요
So it's a it's a good balanced metric that weighs up absolute differences and relative percentage differences.
절대적인 차이와 상대적인 퍼센트 차이를 측정하는 균형 잡힌 측정법이죠
Um, appropriately.
적절하죠
So that's something that we'll be looking at too.
그것도 살펴볼 거예요
Another one that people often look at is much simpler is just mean squared error, which is the the
사람들이 훨씬 단순하게 생각하는 또 다른 건 평균 제곱 오류입니다
square of the difference between the prediction and the actual price.
예측과 실제 가격 사이의 차이의 제곱을 의미하죠
The challenge with mean squared error is that it blows up for larger prices.
제곱 오차의 문제는 가격이 높아도 터질 수 있다는 거죠
So if we have something that costs $800 and we predict $900, then there's a difference of $100 there.
800달러가 드는 것이 있고 900달러가 들 것으로 예상한다면 100달러 차이가 나는 거죠
And if you square that, you get 10,000, which is a big number and which will dwarf all of your other
그걸 제곱하면 10,000가 되죠 아주 큰 숫자입니다 다른 모든 오류가 작아질
errors.
거예요
So mean squared error can be more troubling for our kind of problem.
비열한 제곱 오차는 우리 같은 문제에선 더 큰 골칫거리죠
So those are the model centric metrics.
그게 모델 중심 지표예요
But now let's talk about the business metrics.
이제 비즈니스 지표에 대해 얘기해 보죠
So the wonderful thing about our problem is that there is this metric which is really it's really belongs
우리 문제의 멋진 점은 측정법이 있다는 거예요 양쪽 진영에
in both camps.
속해 있죠
It's just the the average absolute price difference.
평균 절대 가격 차이죠
Basically how wrong was the model.
모델도 잘못됐고요
It said that the fridge cost 100 bucks and it actually cost 120 bucks.
냉장고 가격이 100달러라고 했는데 120달러였어요
So it was out by 20.
20점 차로 졌어요
That average price difference is so simple, so human, understandable.
평균 가격 차이는 단순하고 인간적이며 이해할 만하죠
And that is a great business outcome metric.
그건 훌륭한 비즈니스 결과 척도예요
It has some flaws.
결점이 좀 있어요
It's sort of unfair that that more expensive things like something again that costs like $800 if you're
좀 불공평해요 800달러 정도 하는 더 비싼 것이 850달러라고
out, if you if you guess that it costs $850, you didn't do badly.
추측했다면 나쁘지 않은 거예요
But that's going to count as a $50 error, which is quite significant.
50달러 오류로 간주됩니다 꽤 중요한 거죠
Whereas if something costs $10, $10, then you would want to do much better than be out by $50.
10달러짜리 물건이라면 50달러보다 훨씬 싸게 팔아야 해요
So it's not ideal.
이상적인 상황은 아니죠
It has some some problems, but it's it's pretty good.
문제가 좀 있지만 꽤 괜찮아요
And it's going to give us such a human understandable way of telling whether our model is doing any
우리 모델이 좋은 일을 하는지 인간적으로 이해할 수 있는 방법을 제공할
good.
거예요
In conjunction with that, we could look at the percentage price difference, uh, you know, which
그것과 함께 가격 차이도 살펴볼 수 있어요 반대의
which has the opposite problem.
문제가 있죠
That's sort of more makes more sense, more reasonable for high priced items, but seems a bit unfair
비트 박스가 더 합리적이고 고가의 물품에는 더 합리적이지만 저렴한 물품에는 불공평한
for cheap items.
것 같아요
Something costs ten bucks and you get 12.
10달러짜리 물건에 12달러씩 얹어 주죠 Get it
Then saying that that's 20% out seems a bit a bit harsh.
그런데 20% 비트는 건 좀 심하네요
Um, and then another way to do it is to have some criteria that you will use to judge that an estimate
또 다른 방법은 견적서의 품질을 판단하는 기준을 갖는 겁니다 견적서는
is good quality, and that criteria could combine an absolute difference and a percentage difference.
절대적인 차이와 퍼센트 차이를 합칠 수 있죠
You might say, look, if something is, is, um, either within $40 or it's within 20%, then I consider
오차가 40달러 이하나 20% 이하면 히트라고 볼 수 있죠
I consider that a good estimate.
좋은 추정이네요
Good enough, good enough estimate.
그 정도면 충분해요
Um, and so then you could just measure what percentage of the model's predictions meet that criteria
그러면 모델의 예측이 그 기준에 부합하고 좋다고 간주되는 비율을
and are considered good.
측정할 수 있죠
So that's another business metric that we could use and that we will use.
우리가 사용할 수 있고 또 사용할 또 다른 비즈니스 지표죠
Uh, and so these these are ways that we can assess the performance.
이렇게 성능을 평가할 수 있어요
And as I say, the delight with our project is that they're going to be so human.
우리 프로젝트의 기쁨은 그들이 인간적이라는 거죠
Understandable.
이해해요
So we're going to be able to do things like try different model, different hyperparameters.
다른 모델, hyperpaameter 같은 걸 시도해볼 수 있어요
We're going to try different models.
다른 모델을 시도해 보죠
We're going to try frontier and open source.
프런티어와 오픈 소스를 시도해 보려고요
And we'll simply be able to see which ones are better able to predict product prices.
어떤 회사가 제품 가격을 더 잘 예측하는지 쉽게 알 수 있죠
And so we are very nearly ready to roll our sleeves up and get coding and get assessing how this performs,
이제 소매를 걷어붙이고 코딩을 시작하고 성능을 평가하고 가격을 예측할 준비가 거의 다 됐어요
how we can predict prices.
get it
And it's going to be such a lot of fun.
정말 재미있을 거예요
Uh, but there are just a couple of housekeeping things we have to do first.
하지만 그 전에 몇 가지 정리할 게 있어요
I want to talk to you a bit about, uh, the sort of business This strategy for how you go about solving
비즈니스 전략에 대해 좀 더 얘기하고 싶어요 이런 문제를 해결하는 방법에
a problem like this.
대해서요
And I realize that if you're like me, you are itching to get into it, itching to get in, to actually
여러분도 저와 같다면 들어가고 싶어 안달일 겁니다 드디어 우리 모델을 훈련하고
finally building training our model and seeing how good are these different models out there.
이 다양한 모델이 얼마나 좋은지 보고 싶어 하죠 get it
Um, but I just want to give you this, this grounding, this foundation, so that you have this context
하지만 저는 이 기반과 기반을 알려드리고 싶어요 그래야 사업 문제를 해결하러
that's going to be reinforced when we then do go and solve the business problem.
갔을 때 이 맥락을 강화할 수 있으니까요
I'm going to contrast the different techniques for improving performance and explain, like what's the
퍼포먼스 향상을 위한 다양한 기술을 대조하고 그 차이점을 설명할 거예요
I really want to to clarify, in what circumstances do you use Rag?
어떤 상황에서 랙을 쓰는지 확실히 하고 싶어요
In what circumstances do you use fine tuning?
어떤 상황에서 세세한 조율을 사용하나요?
It's a question I get asked a lot.
Get it, Get it, Get it, Get it, Get it, Get it. 많이 듣는 질문이에요
Um, and I think it's helpful to clarify that before we get into it.
get it 시작하기 전에 명확히 하는 게 도움이 될 것 같아요
So you've got that, that, that context, and then we still have some, some homework to do with the
컨텍스트를 보았고 데이터 집합에 대한 숙제가 아직 남아 있어요
We've still got to curate and upload our final data set.
최종 데이터 세트를 큐레이팅하고 업로드 해야 해요
It's going to be big.
엄청날 거예요
It's going to be a big data set, because we're going to want to do a lot of training.
빅데이터 집합이 될 거예요 훈련을 많이 해야 하니까요
So we have some more to do there.
아직 할 일이 남았어요
All of that, all of that coming tomorrow.
내일이면 모든 게 끝나요
See you then.
그때 봐요